Peter Smith Papers
Peter Smith Papers
1763-1850
Smith, Peter, 1768-1837.
16.0 linear ft.
Papers of the New York State merchant and landowner; father of Gerrit Smith. Collection contains correspondence (1791-1837); financial papers (1771-1850) relating to various business enterprises; business and land papers (1767-1850); legal documents (1772-1840); and writings, including a journal of a trip from Albany to Johnstown in 1822. Notable correspondents include John Jacob Astor, Daniel Cady, William E. Dodge, Abraham Herring, Elbert Herring, Thomas Herring, Samuel Hoard, Nehemiah Huntington, Elisha Kane, John Kiersted, William Laight, William Lamont, Robert Lenox, John Lincklaen, Samuel McNeil, Morris S. Miller, Stephen Parkhurst, Samuel H. Payne, Jonas Platt, Harmon Pumpelly, Zebulon Shipherd, Gerrit Smith, Ezra Stiles, David Tomlinson, Lawrence Vrooman, Nathan Ward, and Elisha Williams.
148672
Biographical History
Peter Gerrit Smith (1768-1837), landowner and father of reformer Gerrit Smith, was a man of significant influence during the first quarter of the nineteenth century in Madison County, New York, where he was active in business, politics, and land transactions, and owner of a large portion of the central and northern sections of the country. In some of his ventures he was the partner of John Jacob Astor. The town of Peterboro, New York is named for him.
Peter Smith was born in Greenbush, Rockland County, New York, on November 15, 1768, the son of Gerrit P. and Wyntje Lent Smith, both of Dutch extraction. In 1784 he entered the counting house of Abraham Herring & Co. in New York City as a clerk. When he was nineteen, he opened a store at Fall Hill, near Little Falls, New York. During these years he went into partnership with John Jacob Astor in the fur trade, and although the parternship lasted only about a year, Smith and Astor continued for many years in the joint business of buying and selling land. Smith acquired a large fortune over the years by shrewd procedures in land transactions, both with Astor and alone, handling about a half a million acres in sum.
In 1789, Peter Smith moved to Old Fort Schuyler, now Utica, where he established a store and continued his speculations in land. In 1794, Astor and William Laight bought the Charlotte River and Byrne's Patent of 37,200 acres in the Mohawk Valley; Astor lent Smith the money to purchase half of the tract. In 1829 Smith bought out his two partners and became owner of the entire patent.
Smith obtained another large tract, this time 50,000 acres, from the Oneida Indians in 1793. He had established friendly relations with them, among whom he seems to have exerted some influence, and had become a close friend of the Oneida Chief Skenandoah, for whom he named his first son, Peter Skenandoah Smith. This "New Petersburgh Tract" comprised the town of Augusta in Oneida County, and the towns of Stockbridge, Smithfield, Fenner and northern Cazenovia in Madison County. Federal law forbade the Indians to sell their land, so Smith leased it for 21 years. In 1795 the state purchased a large part of the Oneida Reservation, including Smith's tract. He had leased portions of it to white settlers; now he and they had to pay the state about $3.50 per acre to obtain their patents. Smith emerged from this transaction with about 22,300 acres.
By 1806 Smith had established the town of Smithfield and, within it, the village of Peterboro. The village consisted of ten buildings including Smith's own house, which became known as the Mansion House in later years after it was enlarged by Peter's son Gerrit.
In 1807 the first officers of Madison County were elected and Peter Smith, a confirmed Federalist, was elected supervisor of the town of Smithfield at its first town meeting. That same year he was appointed judge of the Madison County Court. Smith began publication of the Madison Freeholder, of which he was the "proprietor," in 1808 in Peterboro. This and another publication started simultaneously in another town in Madison County were the first news and literary papers in the area.
On February 5, 1792 Peter Smith married Elizabeth Livingston, daughter of revolutionary army Colonel James Livingston. The records indicate that at least three of their children grew to adulthood: Cornelia, Peter Skenandoah, and Gerrit. Elizabeth died in 1818, and in 1823 Smith married his second wife, Sarah Pogson of Charleston, South Carolina. This marriage was unsuccessful and short-lived, ending in a separation and Sarah's return to Charleston.
Smith lived in Peterboro until 1819, carrying out his public duties, managing his lands and related businesses, and raising his family. In 1819 he turned over the management of his estates and businesses to his son Gerrit, retaining the income of $125,000 for his own use and spending much of his time in traveling. For many years he had been concerned about the state of his soul, and after the death of his first wife his religious concerns grew to a near obsession. He was active in the Madison County Bible Society and American Tract Society, and as he traveled he made it his business to distribute religious tracts in every community he visited.
Smith finally settled in Schenectady in 1825. He had been a man of personal as well as religious peculiarities for much of his life, and despite his financial successes he grew morose at the end, claiming that he was "a trouble to himself and a vexation to those about him." He died at Schenectady on April 14, 1837.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Peter Smith Papers are divided into correspondence, business and land files, and writings.
Correspondence, 1791-1837, includes incoming letters and drafts of outgoing letters. There are approximately 1,580 incoming letters. The correspondence is concerned primarily with Smith's business and land interests, although there is reference to politics, religion and family affairs. Notable correspondents include John Jacob Astor, Daniel Cady, William E. Dodge, Abraham Herring, Elbert Herring, Thomas Herring, Samuel Hoard, Nehemiah Huntington, Elisha Kane, John Kiersted, William Laight, William Lamont, Robert Lenox, John Lincklaen, Samuel McNeil, Morris S. Miller, Stephen Parkhurst, Samuel H. Payne, Jonas Platt, Harmon Pumpelly, Zebulon Shipherd, Gerrit Smith, Ezra Stiles, David Tomlinson, Lawrence Vrooman, Nathan Ward, and Elisha Williams.
A revised index to the correspondence, prepared by staff, indexes all incoming, outgoing and other letters. Correspondents are listed alphabetically by last name and then chronologically under each name. If there is more than one letter from the same person on the same day, each letter is listed individually. Unidentified correspondence are listed at the end. This index may be found at the end of this inventory (if viewing the paper copy), or in PDF form (if viewing online; file is large and may take several seconds to load).
Outgoing letters are primarily drafts prepared by Smith himself, usually in pencil, for his clerk to copy. The earliest separate draft is dated 1800. Notes concerning Smith's replies begin to appear on some letters around 1813, and complete drafts on the incoming letter begin around 1816. Drafts of Smith's correspondence to John Jacob Astor date from 1808 to 1829. All told there are approximately 180 separate drafts of Smith's replies; in the index mentioned above, incoming letters that carry complete drafts of replies are indicated by asterisks (*). A few other letters that were not written to or by Smith are also included in the index.
Business and land files (1763-1850) contains SMith's extensive business, legal and financial papers relating to his large land holdings in central New York. A detailed listing of this material, subdivided into financial documents, land documents, legal documents, and subject files, is given in the inventory below. In organizing these subseries, loose papers were interfiled with bound volumes to preserve chronological continuity. In the inventory below, brackets are used to indicate supplied titles (that is, the volume had no title so one was given to it by staff). It should be noted that the terms "Blotter" and "Day Book" were used synonymously.
Financial documents (1771-1850) include Smith's miscellaneous account books, as well as account books for the Old Fort Schuyler store,the Oriskany Creek store, and the Peterboro store. Also included in this subseries are bank deposit and withdrawal records, bills and receipts, lists of outstanding loans, orders drawn, and miscellaneous material.
Land documents (1767-1850) include descriptions of lots and acreage, lists of land holdings, and the names and maps of military tract grantees. Also included are records of land purchases and sales, primarily relating to the New Petersburgh tract (formerly part of the Oneida Indian Reservation), lands purchased from New York State at tax sales, the Charlotte River and Byrne's Patent, and the Old Military Tract; this section includes surveyors' documents and some maps relating to these lands.
Legal documents (1772-1840) relate primarily to Smith's extensive land holdings and his position as county judge. Included in this subseries are land purchase agreements, bonds, charges to the grand jury, contracts for land sales, deeds and indentures, leases, mortgages, powers of attorney, promissory notes, legal suits, summonses and complaints, and miscellaneous legal documents.
Subject files (1793-1837) includes financial papers regarding Smith's grindstone business; his lease with the Oneida Indians for a portion of their reservation; financial, land and legal records relating to his partnership with John Jacob Astor and William Laight for the purchase of Charlotte's River and Byrne's Patent; and a copy of the will of Sir William Johnson and assorted related papers resulting from the struggles of Astor, Laight and Smith to get clear title to the Charlotte's River and Byrne's Patent.
Writings (1798-1821) contains Smith's miscellaneous prose and verse, and a journal of a trip from Albany to Johnstown in 1822.
After about 1818 Gerrit Smith assumed more and more of his father's business obligations; researchers interested in this later period should consult the
Gerrit Smith Papers
.
Other Formats Available
The entire collection is also available on microfilm (Microfilm #3997).
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically by year, month and day. Letters dated only to the year are placed at the beginning of that year. All undated correspondence is placed at the end of the series and arranged alphabetically by author's last name.
Business and land files are subdivided as described above, and within each subseries arranged roughly chronologically. Writings are in alphabetical order by subject or title.
Related Material
has the papers of many members of the Smith family. See also the
Gerrit Smith Miller Papers
, the
Gerrit Smith Papers
, and the
Greene Smith Papers
. In addition, many monographs, pamphlets and other printed material by or about the Smith family have been cataloged. Please refer to to locate related manuscript collections, and to to locate cataloged printed material.
Other Related Finding Aids
A complete index to the correspondence is available at the end of this inventory (if viewing the hard copy) or in PDF form (if viewing online). The file is large and may take several seconds to load.
A cartobibliography, containing a list of maps and plans in the Peter and Gerrit Smith Papers, and an index of place names, was compiled by library staff in 1989. For each map or plan listed, the guide gives date, author (surveyor), title, dimensions, scale, place names, personal names, and notes. (WARNING: This file is quite large and may take some time to download/open.)
Subject and Genre Headings
Business and Industry; New York State; Astor, John Jacob, 1763-1848.; Cady, Daniel, 1773-1859.; Dodge, William E. (William Earl), 1805-1883.; Herring, Abraham.; Herring, E. (Elbert), 1777-1876.; Herring, Thomas.; Hoard, Samuel.; Huntington, Nehemiah, 1776-1855.; Kane, Elisha.; Kiersted, John.; Laight, William.; Lamont, William.; Lenox, Robert, 1759-1839.; Lincklaen, John, 1768-1822.; McNeil, Samuel.; Miller, Morris S. (Morris Smith), 1779-1824.; Parkhurst, Stephen.; Payne, Samuel H.; Platt, Jonas, 1769-1834.; Pumpelly, Harmon.; Shipherd, Zebulon Rudd, d. 1841.; Smith, Gerrit, 1797-1874.; Smith, Peter, 1768-1837.; Stiles, Ezra.; Tomlinson, David, Esq.; Vrooman, Lawrence.; Ward, Nathan.; Williams, E. (Elisha), 1757-1845.; Land grants -- New York (State); Land titles -- New York (State); Landowners -- New York (State); Oneida Indians.; Madison County (N.Y.) -- History.; New York (State) -- History -- 1775-1865.; Peterboro (N.Y.); Account books.; Bills of sale.; Correspondence.; Daybooks.; Deeds.; Diaries.; Land surveys.; Leases.; Legal documents.; Mortgages.; Promissory notes.; Landowners.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Gerrit Smith Miller, 1928.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  A complete index to the correspondence is available at the end of this inventory (if viewing the hard copy) or in PDF form (if viewing online). The file is large and may take several seconds to load.
  - [General], 1791-1807 (Box 1)
  - [General], 1890-1818 (Box 2)
  - [General], 1819-1825 (Box 3)
  - [General], 1826-1832 (Box 4)
  - [General], 1833-1837 (Box 5)
  - Undated letters (Box 5)
  - Letters without year dates (Box 5)
  - Fragments (Box 5)
- Business and land files
  - Financial documents
    - Account books
      - Miscellaneous
        - Petty Ledger, 1819-1820 (Box 6)
        - C[anastota] & Morrisville Plank Road Company, 1849-1850; treasurer's accounts (Box 6)
        - "Peter Smith, Schenectady, May 1825", 1815-1830 (Box 6)
        - Miscellaneous accounts of Peter Smith, 1819-1822 (Box 6)
        - "Peter Smith's of Peterboro, Schenectady, Memos & Accts., 1826 et sub.", 1813-1814 (Box 6)
        - "Lattu Pain's Account of Sundries. Likewise of work done by him -- Memorandum of work generally", 1808-1820 (Box 6)
      - Peter Smith's waste book, journal and ledger, 1808-1826 (Box 6)
      - "Transactions & Memorandum of Office of Sherrif, Peter Smith, 1795, Herkimer County", 1795-1806; 1803-1807; also "Blotter F," Whitestown and Peterboro (Box 6)
      - "Peter Smith, Blotter, Peterboro, 13 May to 30 Nov 1806" (Box 6)
      - Household accounts, Schenectady, 1825-1836 (Box 6)
      - Peter Smith, New York City, account book, 1785-1787; due to poor condition, the last pages of this volume were not filmed for the microfilm edition (Box 6)
      - Old Fort Schuyler Store
        - Blotter A, Jun 1789-Apr 1791 (Oversize 1)
        - Blotter B, 1791; not filmed (Oversize 2)
        - Blotter C, 9 Jan 1792-20 Aug 1793 (Box 7)
        - Blotter D, 22 Aug 1793-29 Mar 1799 (Box 7)
        - Blotter E, 29 Mar 1799-6 Jan 1803; also includes "Accounts from Oriskany Creek store, Town of Paris, Herkimer County, 1796" (Box 7)
        - "Abstract from old Indian Blotter from 10 November 1788 to 1 August 1791, then commencing Blotter" for Old Fort Schuyler Store, 1788-1802 (Box 8)
        - Ledger A, 1789-1792 (Box 8)
        - Ledger B, 1791-1798 (Box 8)
      - Oriskany Creek store, Town of Paris, Herkimer County
        - Day book, 1796-1798 (Box 8)
        - Accounts, 1796; see Old Fort Schuyler store, Blotter E.
        - Peter Smith's accounts with the Oriskany Creek store; with John Goldsmith; with James Livingston, Jr. & Co., New Petersburgh, 1796-1802 (Box 8)
      - Peterboro store
        - Blotter G, 19 Nov 1807-20 Jul 1819 (Oversize 3)
        - Blotter 1, Nov 1819-Feb 1820 (Box 8)
        - Blotter 2, Feb-May 1820 (Box 8)
        - [Blotter 3 has not been identified in these papers]
        - Blotter 4, Jan-Sep 1821 (Box 8)
        - Day book A, Nov 1819-Nov 1820 (Box 9)
        - Day book, Nov 1820-Jan 1821 (Box 9)
      - Williams and Smith, 1818-1837; account of land sales, Madison County (Box 9)
    - Bank books
      - Bank of Albany, 1801-1822 (Box 9)
      - Mechanics and Farmers Bank, 1811-1837; 3 volumes (Box 9)
      - Mohawk Bank, 1825-1837; 2 volumes (Box 9)
      - Utica Bank, 1825 (Box 9)
      - Manhattan Branch Bank, Utica, 1811-1817 (Box 9)
    - Bills and receipts
      - [General], 1771-1810; 3 folders (Box 9)
      - [General], 1811-1834; 8 folders (Box 10)
      - [General], 1835-1837; 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Undated (Box 11)
    - Loans outstanding, 1790-1836; 3 items (Box 11)
    - Orders drawn, 1820-1821 (Box 11)
    - Miscellaneous material
      - Financial material formerly arranged with correspondence, 1794-1837; undated (Box 11)
      - Material relating to Edward W. and Henry Laight, 1829-1835; 4 items (Box 11)
      - Material relating to Indian business, 1792-1793; 2 items (Box 11)
      - Other material, mostly financial, 1794-1837; undated (Box 11)
  - Land documents
    - Descriptions of lots and acreage, 1806; 1814-1833,; undated; 3 folders (Box 11)
    - Land books forwarded to Federal Dana, circa 1825-1829; 2 volumes (Box 11)
    - Lists of land, 1805-1817 (Box 11)
    - Lists of land, 1818-1846 (Box 12)
    - Military tract guarantees, names and maps, undated (Box 12)
    - Purchases and sales
      - Miscellaneous notes, 1797-1840; 2 folders (Box 12)
      - Land purchases and sales book A for New Petersburgh, in two sections; also, accounts of land purchased from and sold to the State of New York and the Oneida Indians, 1793-1831 (Box 12)
      - Waste book, land sales and payments, 1802-1811 (Box 12)
      - Land purchases and sales book B, 1810-1836 (Box 13)
      - "State of New York. The pieces of parcels of Land described in this Book were purchased at the Comptroller's Sales for Taxes in November 1815 by Elisha Williams and Peter Smith…", 1816-1833 (Box 13)
      - "Lands purchased for Taxes in November 1815 & Deeded on 14 January 1818 by the Comptroller…", 1818-1837 (Box 13)
      - "Marsh Tax Purchased, 1828, 1830, 1834; Tax Purchases, 1821; Road Tax Purchases, 1825, 1831, 1834; and Quit Rent Purchases, 1826, 1821-1836" (Box 13)
      - Sales of land in Tompkins, Chemung, Tioga and Madison Counties, 1830-1839 (Box 14)
      - Sales of land, unidentified, 1815-1834 (Box 14)
      - "Real Estate of Peter Smith. Sales and Purchases made subsequently to 1 Nov 1819, Book D," with index, 1824-1849 (Box 14)
      - Real Estate of Peter Smith, book E, with index, 1824-1849 (Box 14)
      - Real Estate of Peter Smith, book F, with index, 1828-1847 (Box 15)
      - Charlotte River and Byrne's Patent, Laight, Astor and Smith, blotter of Peter Smith, 1796-1815 (Box 15)
      - Charlotte River and Byrne's Patent, Laight, Astor and Smith, blotter B, 1814-1837 (Box 16)
      - Charlotte River and Byrne's Patent, state of unsold lands on Jan. 1, 1827 (Box 16)
      - Estate of Peter Smith, executor's book, list of goods and lands, 1837-1847 (Box 16)
      - "Peter Smith's Day Book or Extracts from Blotter for 1789-1791"; Canajoharie, 1788-1792; Day book of land sales, 1793-1795; and "Sales at Auction of Lands in New Petersburgh, June, 1802", 1788-1802 (Box 16)
      - Old Military Tract, 1829-1837; record of various land purchases and sales (Box 17)
      - Old Military Tract, 1835-1842; record book no. 2 of various land purchases and sales (Box 17)
    - Redemption certificates from the State of New York for overdue taxes on land, 1799-1826; 4 folders (Box 17)
    - Redemption certificates from the State of New York for overdue taxes on land, 1827-1837; 3 folders (Box 18)
    - Surveyor's documents
      - General
        - Survey of the third and fourth townships of the Chenango Triangle, Nathaniel Locke, surveyor, undated (Box 18)
        - Survey, Brant Lake Tract, undated (Box 18)
        - Survey, unidentified, undated (Box 18)
        - Survey, unidentified, undated (Box 18)
        - "Field Book of a Survey of Land Laying Between the Dil[ ]way and Sisquehanna River Beginning on Monday 12th Sept. 176[8]," Archibald Campbell, Surveyor, 1798; not filmed due to deterioration (Box 18)
        - "Fieldbook & Maps of part of No. 3 Manlius, and of lot No. 3, Late Oneida Reservation, 1806," W. Hammond, Surveyor (Box 18)
        - "A Survey of the Village of Peterboro in the County of Chenango…in the Tract Called New-Petersburgh, Made for Peter Smith, Esquire in the Years 1799 & 1804 by Ch. C. Brodhead", 1799-1820 (Box 18)
        - "Field Notes of a Survey of lands in the Village of Petersburgh for Peter Smith Esquire, performed in Sept., 1804, by C. C. Brodhead" (Box 18)
        - "Survey of Lots in New Petersburgh, April 1805, by C.C. Brodhead" (Box 18)
        - "A Survey of Township No 4 [Town of Florence, Oneida County] Scriba's Patent, the Property of William Henderson. Surveyed into Lotts by Benj. Wright", undated (Box 18)
        - "Surveys for the Honbl. Peter Smith Esquire, in September & October, 1816, by Jno. Kiersted", includes part of the former Oneida Indian Reservation (Box 18)
        - "Survey and description of lands in the Chenango Triangle. Conveyed to Peter Smith Esq. & Dr. John D. Henry in June, July and August of 1816. By William R. Finn,, Surveyor" (Box 18)
        - "A Survey of the subdivision of sundry lots, and parts of lots, in Township Number 2 of Chenango Triangle. In the Towns of Smithville and Greene and County of Chenango. The Property of the Hon. Peter Smith Esquire and Doctr. John D. Henry. By Jno. Diersted, AD 1816" (Box 19)
        - "Fieldnotes of lots No 48, 61 and 67, in the third allotment of the Royal Grant, so subdivided in May 1800 by Werden Hammond for Peter Smith", 1800-1818 (Box 19)
        - Map and survey of lot no. 31, Cicero, 13 May 1819 (Box 19)
        - "A Survey of certain lots and parts of lots in Township No. 4 in Scriba's Patent, Town of Florence, County of Oneida," Issac Bumpus, surveyor, 1822 (Box 19)
        - Survey of lot no. 54, Groton, 1819 (Box 19)
        - "Field Book, Chenango Triangle, First Township", 1826 (Box 19)
        - "Field Book, Chenango Triangle, Township No. Two", 1826 (Box 19)
        - Surveys and maps for portions of the Old Military Tract and other tracts, 1829-1842 (Box 19)
        - "New Petersburgh Tract, 2nd Allotment, Field Book, June 8, 1831" (Box 19)
        - "Macomb's Purchase. Great Tract One, Township 14S., 1/2 thereof and Township 14N.E., 1/4 thereof. Field Book of 108 Lots as Surveyed in the year 1835 by Nathan Ward" (Box 19)
        - [Chenango Triangle,] field book, David S. Crandall, surveyor, 1830; 1824-1832 (Box 19)
      - Charlotte River and Byrne's Patent (Box 19)
        - Outbounds of Byrne's Tract, Christopher Yates, surveyor; also, records of allotments by Ph. Freye, 1767; 1795 (Box 19)
        - Field notes of a survey of Byrne's Patent books 1-4, 1799-1801 (Box 19)
        - "A Survey of Lands In Byrne's Patent Performed in 1799 & 1800 for Peter Smith Esquire by Ch. C. Brodhead, Books 1 & 2" (Box 19)
        - "A Survey of Lands In Byrne's Patent Performed in 1799 & 1800 for Peter Smith Esquire by Ch. C. Brodhead. Being the property of Peter Smith, William Laight, and John Jacob Astor, books 1 & 2" (Box 19)
        - "Field Book of the Lots in Charlotte River Patent Surveyed for Peter Smith Esq. and not appraised by Commissioners...", 1803 (Box 19)
        - "Field Book of the Lots in Charlotte River Patent Surveyed for Peter Smith Esq. and appraised by Commissioners...", 1803 (Box 19)
        - "Charlotte River Traverse by C.C. Brodhead, August, 1803" (Box 19)
        - "Charlotte Field Book Begun May 25, 1804, Closed June 7, Seth Ensign" (Box 19)
        - Charlotte River survey conducted by Charles C. Brodhead, 1804 (Box 20)